They had nothing to lose, they risked it all.
The Commitments is a comedy, drama, music film directed by Alan Parker.
Jimmy Rabbitte, just a thick-ya out of school, gets a brilliant idea: to put a
soul band together in Barrytown, his slum home in north Dublin.
First he needs musicians and singers: things slowly start to click when he finds three fine-voiced females virtually in his back
yard, a lead singer (Deco) at a wedding, and, responding to his ad, an aging trumpet player, Joey "The Lips" Fagan.
Jimmy Rabbitte, played by Robert Arkins.
Steven Clifford, played by Michael Aherne.
Imelda Quirke, played by Angeline Ball.
Natalie Murphy, played by Maria Doyle Kennedy.
Mickah Wallace, played by Dave Finnegan.
Bernie McGloughlin, played by Bronagh Gallagher.
The Commitments is a 1991 musical comedy-drama film
based on the 1987 novel by Roddy Doyle.
It was directed by Alan Parker from a screenplay written
by Doyle, Dick Clement and Ian La Frenais.
Set in the Northside of Dublin, the film tells the story of Jimmy Rabbitte (Robert Arkins), a young music
fanatic who assembles a group of working-class youths to form a soul band named "The Commitments".
The film is the first in a series known as The Barrytown Trilogy,
followed by The Snapper (1993) and The Van (1996).
Producers Lynda Myles and Roger Randall-Cutler acquired the film rights to the novel in 1988,
and commissioned Doyle, a first-time screenwriter, to write an adaptation.
Doyle spent one year working on the script before Myles brought in veteran
screenwriters Clement and La Frenais to help complete it.
Upon reading the novel, Parker signed on as the film's director in 1989.
An international co-production between Ireland, the United States and the United Kingdom, The Commitments was
the first film produced by Beacon Pictures, which provided an estimated budget of $12–15 million.
The film's young lead actors were mostly inexperienced, and were cast because of their
musical backgrounds and resemblance to the characters in the novel.
Principal photography took place in Dublin, from late August to October, 1990.
The Commitments underperformed at the North American box office,
grossing $14.9 million during its theatrical run.
Reviewers praised the music, performances and humour, while criticism was
occasionally aimed at the pacing and Parker's direction.
The film resulted in two soundtrack albums released by MCA Records; the first reached number eight on the Billboard
200 album chart and achieved triple-platinum status, while the second album achieved gold sales status.
At the 1992 British Academy Film Awards, the film won four of six BAFTA Awards for
Best Film, Best Direction, Best Adapted Screenplay and Best Editing.
It also received an Academy Award nomination for Best Film Editing.
The film has since gained cult status.
The film explores themes of dublin, ireland, ireland,
soul music, band, the barrytown trilogy.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.